Narrator: The Pitt Rivers Museum in Oxford was founded in 1884, by Augustus Pitt Rivers,
a British army officer, ethnologist, and archaeologist.
The displays were installed by its first curator, Henry Balfour,
and catalogued by the anthropologist, Beatrice Blackwood.
And today, this eccentric and quirky space is like a trip back in time.
It’s crammed with around 55,000 objects on display,
ranging from prehistoric handaxes and a witch in a bottle,
to a mask with movable eyes, and a leaf-shaped dagger.
And behind the scenes, the museum, looks after another 550,000 items,
cataloguing, conserving, and studying the many different historic items it houses.
The Pitt Rivers has often been described as a ‘museum, of a museum’,
feeling at once old and new, traditional and contemporary.
The mix of styles is extremely popular,
with visitor numbers climbing to over 500,000 in the last few years.
A sensitive modernization programme has included the installation of 170 metres of new displays
– that’s almost the length of two Big Bens – the addition of 1,500 new exhibits,
and the digitization of 10,000 photographs.
They’ve even lit up the whole space with tons of energy-efficient LEDs,
transforming many of their displays.
All of this shows that the Pitt Rivers is looking to the future,
but to do so, it also needs to face up to its past.
Like most 19th-century European museums, the Pitt Rivers has its roots in colonialism.
When it opened in 1884, the British Empire stretched from North America to New Zealand
and included large parts of Africa and Asia.
Other European countries, such as Belgium, France, and the Netherlands had similar colonies.
At the time, it was common for these colonial powers to send people across the world,
with the army, to work, for study, or, sometimes, just for fun.
As they travelled, some even chronicled their experiences with the emerging technology of film.
Looking through the Pitt Rivers’ film archive today,
you get a sense of what it was like for these European travellers,
encountering people and places they knew little or nothing about.
They had suddenly discovered new and different landscapes and creatures,
witnessed rituals and religious ceremonies, and been fascinated by the clothes of both rich
and poor, as well as by the local craftsmanship they observed.
But you can also see the colonial mindset,
where what they saw as foreign and exotic was to be captured, relocated,
and displayed for those back home in Europe.
They didn’t just take photos or film.
Before long, items of historical interest were being sent to Europe from all over the world.
Much of the Pitt Rivers’ collection was ‘acquired’ during the heyday of the British Empire
and the museum often reflected these imperial values.
When object labels were written, for example, they used what is now considered derogatory
and shocking language.
When challenged on this in the 1980s, the museum, just painted the offending words out.
But things are changing. And to make this change, the Pitt Rivers is inviting the world in.
Now, other voices are pushing the museum, to reassess its own history.
Some of these are from places where objects in the collection originated.
Representatives from Haida Gwaii, a group of islands between Canada and Alaska,
have been in conversation with both the Pitt Rivers in Oxford and the British Museum in London
to improve relationships between the Haida people and the museums holding their treasures.
For over a century, Haida artefacts have formed an important part of the Pitt Rivers collection.
This includes this Haida war helmet, with its carved and painted octopus,
which the Haida believe was worn by prominent chiefs during battle or ceremonial war dances.
And, of course, there’s the Haida totem pole, which has become a symbol of the museum.
It’s over 11 metres tall, the largest object in the collection,
and shows seated figures and animals such as a bear, a frog, and a raven.
These totems serve many purposes,
such as commemorating important events or telling the stories of the local people.
All of these items still have huge cultural significance to the local people,
something Haida artists Jaalen and Gwaii Edenshaw felt immediately
when they first visited the Pitt Rivers in 2009.
Jaalen: You always feel two ways when you’re in a museum, like that,
‘cos it’s so awesome to be in the presence of all this old Haida things, but at the same time,
you, you know, you feel a sadness because all those things were, ah,
removed from our village and, and by that removing has lost its purpose in our community.
Gwaii: I didn’t expect it actually, but when I walked into the room with the chief’s headdresses,
it was a very emotional experience for me and, er, it caught me off guard.
You know, those pieces felt like they were…lost.
Narrator:  The importance of these items isn’t limited to the objects themselves;
they tell us a huge amount about the cultures they come from.
Take ‘The Great Box’, for example, part of the Pitt Rivers collection since 1874.
We don’t know exactly what it was used for,
but we do know it is a masterpiece of Haida Nation craftsmanship.
That’s why Gwaii and Jaalen decided to create a replica.
The brothers spent 28 days at the museum,
studying the box and re-learning the skills of their ancestors.
Working 12-hour days, they eventually carved a replica and took the new box
– and new skills – back home.
This is just one example of the many projects to welcome more voices to the debate.
The Pitt Rivers has run workshops, seminars, lectures,
and meetings to ensure this difficult history – and the hurt it has caused
– is heard and understood. Of course, this doesn’t right those wrongs,
but by shining a light on its history, the Pitt Rivers is showing that the past belongs to everyone.